Guide to the Robert Landy Papers MC.259
New York University Archives
Robert Landy Papers
1967-2016
New York University Archives
Landy, Robert J.
MC.259
12.5 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 18 manuscript boxes, 2 flat boxes
285.1 Gigabytes in 1,057 computer files
47 sound tape reels
1 Half_Inch_Video_Reel
16 VHS
13 U-matic
Robert Landy (b. 1944) is professor emeritus at New York University's Drama Therapy Program, playwright, and theatre director. He founded the Drama Therapy Program at New York University (NYU) in 1984. In addition to his tenure at NYU, Landy has over 35 years of clinical experience in drama therapy, working with children and adults. The Robert Landy Papers document Landy's intellectual, professional, and artistic activities in theatre, his scholarly writing on drama therapy, and his work as a professor of drama therapy. The collection dates from 1967 to 2016 and includes paper, born-digital, and audiovisual material. The material in the collection includes draft and published versions of scripts, articles, and books written by Landy and others; analog and digital audio and video recordings of plays and theatrical events directed by Landy; notes and other material related to classes taught by Landy at NYU; and notes, correspondence, and publicity material related to international trainings led by Landy. A large part of the collection documents Landy's work on NYU's Sunrise Semester (1979-1981) and his book God Lives in Glass (2001), which he later adapted for the stage.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions, with the following exceptions.
Repository permission is required for access to materials created by children and used in the creation of God Lives in Glass and City Lights Youth Theatre: Standing Tall. Please contact the University Archives, university-archives@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2641.
Material pertaining to individual student records may be restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Biographical Note
Robert Landy (b. 1944) is professor emeritus at New York University's Drama Therapy Program, playwright, and theatre director. He began teaching at New York University (NYU) in 1979 and founded the university's Drama Therapy Program in 1984. In addition to his tenure at NYU, Landy has over 35 of clinical experience in drama therapy, working with children and adults. In the 1979-1980 academic year, he taught the class "Drama in Education" through NYU's televised distance learning program, Sunrise Semester. Since the 1980s, Landy has led trainings for drama therapy professionals and given lectures on drama therapy throughout the United States and other countries. In addition to his work in drama therapy, Landy is also a theatre director and playwright. Since the late 1960s, he has written and directed his own original works, as well as plays he adapted from the works of Horatio Alger and William Shakespeare. Landy has also written books and scholarly articles on drama, drama therapy, and related topics.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Robert Landy in 2015, with additional accretions in 2016 and 2017. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 15.042, 2016.018, 2016.022, 2016.039, 2017.013, and 2019.042.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in alphabetical order by type of material and in alphabetical order by title within that arrangement. Episodes of Sunrise Semester are arranged in chronological order according to the schedule listed in the course outline.
Material that consists of a large amount of paper material or any audiovisual material is listed under its full title. The inventory lists box and folder numbers for an alphabetical range of titles for other material.
Scope and Contents
The Robert Landy Papers document Landy's work in theatre and education between 1967 and 2016. The collection includes paper, born-digital, and audiovisual material documenting his professional and artistic activities in theatre, his work as a professor of drama therapy, and his scholarly writing on drama therapy. Material in the collection includes draft and published scripts, articles, and books written by Landy and others; audio recordings of plays and theatrical events directed by Landy; material related to classes taught by Landy at NYU; and material related to trainings in drama therapy led by Landy in the United States (US), Europe, and Asia. The bulk of the collection documents, "Drama in Education", Landy's class taught through NYU's television program Sunrise Semester (1979-1981); his files on classes taught through NYU's Drama Therapy program in the 2000s; and his book God Lives in Glass (2001), which he later adapted for the stage. The God Lives in Glass paper material includes original artwork by children, forms used during interviews with the children, drafts of the book and play. There are also audio recordings of the play God Lives in Glass and scanned copies of notes and forms used by Landy in the course of his research for the book. Landy's work as a playwright and theatre director is documented though published and draft scripts, notes, photographs, audio recordings of performances, and publicity materials for plays. The scripts include original compositions by Landy and plays adapted by Landy from works by Horatio Alger and William Shakespeare. Included in this material is original correspondence on which Letters from Sing Sing was based, including correspondence between Landy and the man on whom the character of Michael is based.
Material documenting Landy's career as an educator, dates from the late 1970s through the mid 2010s, and includes class outlines, syllabi, notes for lectures, copies of readings for class discussions, and correspondence and awards celebrating Landy's achievements as a professor. This also includes video and audio recordings of "Drama in Education", a class taught by Landy during the academic year of 1979-1980 for NYU's television program Sunrise Semester, as well as paper course outlines, notes, and study guides for the classes. Also included is material documenting Landy's work as a lecturer on drama therapy at National Association for Drama Therapy conferences, and as a trainer leading seminars and workshops on drama therapy. This material dates from the mid 1990s through the mid 2010s, and includes correspondence regarding planning of events, printed publicity materials, video recordings of trainings, and documentation on methods taught at the trainings.
Other material in the collection includes correspondence with colleagues, some files include publications by correspondents and notes by Landy; clippings and publications with articles by and about Landy; and issues of Arts in Psychotherapy, a scholarly journal edited by Landy in the 1990s.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Appraisal
In December 2020 the following were identified as candidates for deaccessioning and were removed from the collection: off-air recording of PBS' Independent Lens, a video introduction for a Chilean drama school, duplicates of Sunrise Semester recordings from Landy's class (not off-air recordings, the original footage), raw footage of healing ceremony in Korea, and video outtakes of play practice and scenes around a theatre. These were removed from the collection because they were materials to which the University Archives could not provide access to, of little or no research value, not related to the collection, or were duplicative material.
Children -- Religious life.; Drama -- Therapeutic use.; American drama -- 20th century.; Distance education.; New York University -- Faculty; Steinhardt School of Education. Drama Therapy Program.
- Conferences, 1984-2012; cuid5197 (Box 9, Folder 1-12)
- Correspondence, 1970-2010; cuid5196
  - Paper Records (Box 8, Folder 8-15)
  - Electronic Records, UA_MC_259_ER_2
- Music and photography, 1978-2010; cuid5213
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 40-42)
  - Electronic Records, UA_MC_259_ER_3
- Teaching -- Ad, 1999-2014; cuid5203
  - Paper Records (Box 11, Folder 1-7)
  - Electronic Records, UA_MC_259_ER_5
- Teaching -- City Lights Youth Theatre: Standing Tall, 2001-2002; cuid5204 (Box 11, Folder 8-10)
- Teaching -- City Lights Youth Theatre: Standing Tall -- Children's writings, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 6-8)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Repository permission is required for access to materials created by children and used in the creation of City Lights Youth Theatre: Standing Tall. Please contact the University Archives, university-archives@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2641.
- Teaching -- Cl - Co, 1972-1995; cuid5205 (Box 11, Folder 11, Box 12, Folder 1-2, Box 23, Folder 1)
- Teaching -- Dialogue with Sue Jennings, 1992-2015; cuid5124; 3 VHS (Box 18, Cassette MC.259.cuid5124a-c)
  Scope and Contents
  (MC.259.cuid5124a) Landy interviews Sue Jennings and the two engage in different forms of drama therapy, including singing, playing hand games, and imitating each other's actions. Jennings discusses different forms drama therapy can take, the role of drama in daily life, and patients with which she has worked.
  (MC.259.cuid5124b) Video is titled Reflections on Drama Therapy and includes footage of small children playing outside and host Bronwen Warren introducing other drama therapists while four people perform on a stage. 26 minutes into the recording it switches to same recording as MC.259.cuid5124a.
- Teaching -- Dis, 2002; cuid5206
  - Paper Records (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Electronic Records, UA_MC_259_ER_7
- Teaching -- Drama Therapy f - Group D, 1988-2016; cuid5207
  - Paper Records (Box 12, Folder 4-8)
  - Electronic Records, UA_MC_259_ER_12
- Teaching -- Drama Therapy, 1979-1981; cuid5184; 1 U-matic Original container is labeled: Drama Therapy. (Box 22, Cassette MC.259.cuid5184)
  Landy sits with students on the floor and introduces the students to the camera people and photographers. The students discuss their feelings about being videotaped and photographed and interact with the cameras. The students work with masks and dolls, discuss each other in terms of roles they are playing, and Landy directs their work.
  Repository permission is required for access. Please contact University Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
- Teaching -- Faculty Series on University Living, 2016; UA_MC_259_ER_13
- Teaching -- Group Thesis Project, 1994; cuid5125; 1 VHS (Box 18, Cassette MC.259.cuid5125)
  Students in masks and costumes perform to pre-recorded music and discuss creating as a group with objects.
- Teaching -- I - P, 1984-2015; cuid5208 (Box 12, Folder 9-13)
- Teaching -- Role Method, 2000-2016; cuid5127; 1 VHS (Box 18, Cassette MC.259.cuid5127)
  Landy lectures on role theory and its effects on his theory of drama therapy. He and the students all state their roles, the students perform in pairs with a third student as a guide, and the class discusses what happened in each encounter.
- Teaching -- Role Theory and Role Method in Drama Therapy, 2016; cuid5209 (Box 12, Folder 14)
- Teaching -- Role Therapy, 2005; cuid5128; 1 VHS (Box 18, Cassette MC.259.cuid5128)
  Landy introduces the lecture on Everett L. Shostrom's 1965 Three Approaches to Psychotherapy and his work to create a modern version of this for drama therapy. Landy demonstrates role method and role theory and answers questions posed by a panel of students.
- Teaching -- Sh - St, 1994-2015; cuid5210
  - Paper Records (Box 12, Folder 15-18)
  - Electronic Records, UA_MC_259_ER_14
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama in Education, 1979-1980; cuid5211 (Box 12, Folder 20)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Overview of the Course, 1979; cuid5135 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5135)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Definitions and Issues in Drama in Education, 1979; cuid5136
  The guest is Lowell Swortzell.
  - Audio, cuid5136 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5136)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- A History of America Drama and Theatre, 1979; cuid5137
  The guest is Nellie McCaslin.
  - Audio, cuid5137 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5137)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama as Process #1: Getting Started, 1979; cuid5138
  - Audio, cuid5138a (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5138a)
  - Video, cuid5138b (Box 21, U-matic MC.259.cuid5138b)
    Original container is labeled: SS-4, SS Sik + Kids.
    The guest is Geraldine Brain Siks. Siks leads a group of children through a series of warm-up exercises and then using objects in imaginative play. At the end of the recording, Siks and the children discuss what they worked on and what they each liked best. Then Landy joins Siks and the two discuss the session.
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama as Process #2: Getting Started (continued), 1979; cuid5139
  The guest is Geraldine Brain Siks.
  - Audio, cuid5139a (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5139a)
  - Video, cuid5139b; 1 U-matic Original containers are labeled: Sunrise Semester Air Master Air: Sept 26 1979 "Getting Started Continued - Part Two" Eps. #5; and SS Sik + kids SS-6.
  - Video, cuid5139c; 1 U-matic Original containers are labeled: Sunrise Semester Air Master Air: Sept 26 1979 "Getting Started Continued - Part Two" Eps. #5; and SS Sik + kids SS-6.
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama as Process #3: Story Dramatization, 1979; cuid5140
  The guest is Coleman Jennings. Landy and Jennings view and discuss a recording of Jennings and a group of children at dramatic play. Jennings and the children engage in imaginative play with objects and he asks the children to pretend to be items from Pandora's Box. After the recording, Landy and Jennings discuss the session.
  - Audio, cuid5140a (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5140a)
  - Video, cuid5140b (Box 21, U-matic MC.259.cuid5140b)
    Original container is labeled: TV Clock Coleman Jennings EPS. #6.
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 13)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama as Process #4: The Child as Playmaker, 1979; cuid5142
  The guest is Carol Korty.
  (MC.259.cuid5142b) Carol Korty and four children set a scene on a stage, with one child directing the others and Korty assisting them. The children each talk about how the scene should be played and how each actor should respond to events in the scene. After the session, Landy joins Korty and they discuss the session, her teaching method, and whether drama would be useful to non-drama educators.
  - Audio, cuid5142a (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5142a)
  - Video, cuid5142b (Box 21, U-matic MC.259.cuid5142b)
    Original container is labeled: SS- Korty SS-7
  - Video, cuid5142c (Box 21, U-matic MC.259.cuid5142c)
    Original container is labeled: SS- Korty SS-8
  - Video, cuid5142d (Box 21, U-matic MC.259.cuid5142d)
    Original container is labeled: SS- Korty SS-9
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Children Talk about Drama, 1979; cuid5141
  Guests include students of Rob Lesser and the 92nd St. Y. Landy discusses drama with four children, two of whom were in the group with Geraldine Brain Siks. He asks the children about what they think drama is, where they learned about drama, and in what form of drama they've participated. He also asks them about imaginative play on their own without an audience and how that differs from performing for an audience.
  - Audio, cuid5141a (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5141a)
  - Video, cuid5141b (Box 21, U-matic MC.259.cuid5141b)
    Cassette is labeled "Children Talk About Drama. Intro: "This morning we have an interesting panel of guests." Original container is labeled SS Landy + Kids #11.
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama as Process #6: Drama in an Inner City School, 1979; cuid5143
  - Audio, cuid5143 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5143)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 14)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama as Process #7: Improvisation, 1979; cuid5145
  The guest is John Hodgson.
  - Audio, cuid5145 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5145)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 15)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama as Process #8: Simulation, 1979; cuid5144
  - Audio, cuid5144 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5144)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 16)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama as Process #9: An Interview with Gavin Bolton, 1979; cuid5146
  Landy interviews Gavin Bolton. Bolton discusses how he became interested in teaching with drama and how he uses drama in his work with troubled youth, in particular having teenagers use role play in order to solve problems. Bolton states his belief that play and spontaneity within a structured exercise hold the greatest potential for learning and shares his definition of process drama.
  - Audio, cuid5146a (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5146a)
  - Video, cuid5146b (Box 21, U-matic MC.259.cuid5146b)
    Original cassette is labeled: Sunrise Semester Mr. Gavin Bolton.
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 17)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Teaching History through Drama #1, 1979; cuid5147
  The guest is Nancy Swortzell.
  - Audio, cuid5147 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5147)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 18)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Teaching History through Drama #2, 1979; cuid5148
  - Audio, cuid5148 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5148)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 19)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Teaching Language Arts through Drama, 1979; cuid5149
  The guest is James Moffett.
  - Audio, cuid5149 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5149)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 20)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Teaching Writing through Drama, 1979; cuid5150 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5150)
  Guests include Linda Balsam and Joan Kaufman.
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Teaching Reading through Drama, 1979; cuid5151
  The guest is Shirlee Sloyer.
  - Audio, cuid5151 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5151)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 21)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Theatre-in-Education: Principles and Practices, 1979; cuid5152
  - Audio, cuid5152 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5152)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 22)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Theatre-in-Education: Practical Application in Schools, 1979; cuid5153 (Box 19, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5153)
  Guests include Lynda Zimmerman and members of the Creative Arts Team at New York University.
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Theatre-in-Education: Practical Application in Schools, 1979; cuid5154
  - Audio, cuid5154 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5154)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 23)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Children Perform the Classics, 1979; cuid5155
  Guests include Phil Lopate, Lisa Cowen, and Angus Johnston. Children perform Anton Chekhov's Uncle Vanya on stage in costume.
  - Audio, cuid5155a (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5155a)
  - Video, cuid5155b (Box 21, U-matic MC.259.cuid5155b)
    Original cassette is labeled: Uncle Vanya SS #5.
  - Paper Records (Box 12, Folder 19, Box 13, Folder 24)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- School Drama as Product: The School Play, 1979; cuid5156
  Guests include Joan Johnston and Michael Tempel.
  - Audio, cuid5156 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5156)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 25)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama in the Community, 1979; cuid5157
  The guest is Richard Courtney. Landy interviews Courtney about using drama in his work with the disabled. He discusses his history of working in therapy and education, what he learned from traditional therapists, and the interaction of patients as human performers.
  - Audio, cuid5157a (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5157a)
  - Video, cuid5157b (Box 21, U-matic MC.259.cuid5157b)
    Original cassette is labeled: #3 Prof Richard Courtney.
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 26)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- The Museum as a Source of Drama Education, 1979; cuid5158
  The guest is Tom Cahill.
  - Audio, cuid5158 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5158)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 27)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Training Counselors through Improvisation, 1979; cuid5159
  Guests include Joyce St. George and Francis P. Canavan.
  - Audio, cuid5159 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5159)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 28)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Exploring Concerns of Teenagers through Drama, 1979; cuid5160 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5160)
  Guests include Edward Welch and three students.
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Sociodrama and Psychodrama in the Community, 1979; cuid5161 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5161)
  The guest is James Sacks.
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama/Theatre for the Handicapped, 1979; cuid5162
  The guests are Karen [Luxton?], Jane [Frannila?], and Elliot Schloss.
  - Audio, cuid5162 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5162)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 29)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Puppetry for/with the Mentally Retarded, 1979; cuid5163 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5163)
  The guest is Lea Wallace.
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama and Therapy, 1979; cuid5172 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5172)
  The guest is Richard Courtney.
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama for/with Emotionally Disturbed Individuals, 1979; cuid5165
  The guest is Gertrud Schattner.
  - Audio, cuid5165a (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5165a)
  - Video, cuid5165b (Box 21, U-matic MC.259.cuid5165b)
    Original container is labeled: CBS-TV Sunrise Semester November 30, 1979 Drama in Education: Drama Therapy with Gertrude Schattner.
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 30)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama/Theatre for/with the Blind, 1979; cuid5166
  The guest is Rick Curry.
  - Audio, cuid5166 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5166)
  - Paper Records (Box 13, Folder 31)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama/Theatre for/with the Orthopedically Handicapped, 1979; cuid5167 (Box 20, Quarter inch audio reel MC.259.cuid5167)
- Teaching -- Sunrise Semester -- Drama/Theatre for/with the Elderly, 1979; cuid5168